The war with Iran has been a major
setback for the United States. None of
its main objectives have been achieved.
The Iranian government is still in
power.
Its nuclear stockpile remains in place.
Its [music] missile and drone
capabilities are largely intact. At the
same time, Tehran has shown that it can
disrupt traffic through the Strait of
Hormuz whenever it wants, giving it the
ability to cause serious economic damage
to its neighbors and beyond.
Welcome everyone to Caspian Report. I'm
your host, Shirwan.
And today's [music] episode is one I've
been looking forward to.
The Strait of Hormuz. That's the
conversation [music]
everyone is having these days.
This is what the situation looks like
right now in [music] real time.
Ships are lining up to pay the toll and
cross the strait, but the number of
vessels going in and out is considerably
lower than before.
This shows ships inbound and these are
the ships outbound.
Meanwhile,
this is the section that's been closed
off by Iran. Any commercial vessel
passing through it without having talked
it over with Iran
will get targeted by them.
Let me just filter the incidents. So,
this right here shows places where ships
were targeted.
By the way, this interface is from our
own app, Delta Sweep. It tracks AIS
feeds in real time and allows you to
monitor activity in the Strait of Hormuz
with unmatched clarity. You can try it
out for yourself at deltasweep.com.
Anyway, tracking these ships is quite
difficult. There is a lot of gray zoning
here. Some ships turn off their tracking
systems, others change flags and names,
and still others essentially transfer
cargo at sea, thereby bypassing
sanctions. [music]
These activities create a shadow fleet
of sorts in and around the Strait of
Hormuz.
It's just something to keep in [music]
mind.
Zooming out, you can see which countries
are the most affected by the closure of
the strait and which are the least
affected. Interesting,
America is among the least [music]
troubled.
Thanks to fracking, the United States
can meet its domestic [music] demand.
This map here shows all the oil and gas
fields worldwide. North America has more
than enough for itself. But now, with
Venezuela under its thumb, refineries in
Texas [music] can turn that Venezuelan
black goo into something [music] useful.
So, perhaps
years from now we could see Venezuelan
oil reaching European markets via the
United States. But right now, with the
closing of the Strait of Hormuz,
some of America's allies are under
stress, particularly Japan, South Korea,
the Philippines,
Thailand, and much of Europe.
If these countries cannot restore stable
energy flows,
their stockpiles will run out in a
matter of months. And so, when Trump
asks European and Asian allies to step
up, to send warships and help open the
strait, he does make a point.
Those countries need the oil and gas
from the Persian Gulf
more than America.
But none of them
want to get their hands dirty.
So, why then does Trump still want to
open the straits? [music]
Well,
energy markets will eventually
compensate.
Even if America has enough oil [music]
to meet its own domestic needs, prices
will surge eventually when global
markets shift.
Also,
>> [music]
>> while Trump has used tough rhetoric
towards allies,
he cannot allow these allies to weaken
to the point that it would affect their
capabilities.
This right here shows all the most
important US military bases abroad.
If these host nations were to decline,
it's really the entire American security
umbrella that would take a hit.
Without those allies, we would see a
downgrade in US [music] power
projection. So, in many ways,
the Hormuz crisis is very much similar
to the Suez crisis of 1956,
which marked [music] the end of the
British and French empires.
If America continues [music] to act
recklessly,
the Hormuz crisis could set in motion
the end of [music] its empire.
So,
Trump wants to avoid that at all costs,
which brings us to the present situation
with Trump negotiating for an exit
strategy.
Now, for Israel,
none of that matters. Israel lives in an
entirely different geopolitical plane.
For the government of Netanyahu, Trump's
deal with Iran
creates anxiety because they would be
expected to live with the consequences
of a deal they did not negotiate.
Not surprisingly, this is generating
friction between Trump and Netanyahu.
Now, that sounds like a very weird thing
to say.
At large, Trump has been a superb ally
to Israel.
Truly one of a kind.
He's delivered plenty of political wins
to Netanyahu.
He's recognized Jerusalem as Israel's
capital,
moved the US embassy there, he's
recognized Israeli sovereignty over the
Golan Heights, and
>> [music]
>> continued military support to Israel
overall. In fact,
>> [music]
>> Trump's support for Israel has been so
profound
that he may actually be more popular in
Israel than Netanyahu is.
But, Israel, and particularly
Netanyahu's government, has many
vulnerabilities [music] and
shortcomings.
Mainly,
none of the battlefield victories that
Israel has scored in recent years
>> [music]
>> have translated into political gains.
None.
Israel has been unable to decisively
crush Iran, Hezbollah, or even Hamas.
>> [music]
>> And so, Netanyahu needs Trump's support
now more than ever.
But, the two
have widely different interests, and
those discrepancies are steadily
surfacing as we're now entering the end
game phase.
The real test [music] is now
the Iran-US negotiations, and how
they're moving toward a memorandum of
understanding.
And, based on what we know from
open-source intelligence, [music]
the new deal with Iran
will be perceived by Israeli policy
makers, including Netanyahu and his
political opponents,
as a lose-lose.
This graph shows the main talking
points, the points of contention.
The black dots represent US positions,
while the red ones illustrates Iran's.
The sticking points range from Iran's
[music]
nuclear program and the Strait of Hormuz
to sanctions relief and security
guarantees, but also ceasefire in
Lebanon and war reparations.
The deal Trump is working on
will have the Iranian theocracy and the
IRGC remain in place. In fact, the
post-war government in Tehran will be
even more hardline than before and there
will be no conditions [music]
for regime change down the line.
What's more, the Iranian government is
now more cohesive
>> [music]
>> than ever before and above all,
they've set a precedent by withstanding
a major US attack and while doing so,
coming up with a new weapon of
deterrence, namely the ability to close
the Strait of Hormuz.
Equally important, despite the massive
US bombing campaign, Iran has shown that
no country can impose serious
restrictions on its [music] nuclear
infrastructure.
Only quickly enabled the nuclear sites.
So, Natanz, for instance,
>> [music]
>> which is here,
was bombed quite heavily, but it's
already showing signs of restoration.
Meanwhile, Pickaxe Mountain, which is
[music] to its south,
is believed to hold the missing 400
kilos of enriched uranium.
60% enriched to be exact, which is very
close to weapons grade in technical
terms.
With just a little more refining, Iran
will have enough material to make about
a dozen bombs, nuclear [music] bombs.
But Pickaxe Mountain is too deep for
even the most sophisticated bunker
buster, so it was largely left intact.
[music]
Anyway, the fact that Iran survived
months of unseen levels of bombardment
has set an important precedent.
What we have now is an Iran that is more
confident than before, more willing to
take risks, less fearful.
And in the years to come, as the country
regains access to its frozen assets,
we will see an Iran that is way stronger
than today.
Every dollar released today could be
tomorrow's drone, proxy operative, or
missile. [snorts]
And after rebuilding and expanding its
conventional capabilities and asymmetric
capabilities,
we will see an Iran that is
>> [music]
>> somewhat
untouchable.
That is to say that the cost of fighting
Iran will vastly outweigh the benefits.
[music]
So, war with Iran
will become highly improbable in years
from now. And once that happens,
inevitably, Iran will go nuclear.
>> [music]
>> Check this.
These are the missiles in Iran's
arsenal. Some go as far as 2,500 km,
but this one in particular,
the Khorramshahr, has a massive payload
capacity.
If any of Iran's missiles are going to
carry nuclear warheads,
>> [music]
>> it will be this one.
The point is that Iran already has the
missiles and fissile material.
And it also has the know-how and
capability
to produce even more.
>> [music]
>> And that's precisely why America insists
on a complete end to its nuclear
enrichment program [music]
and that the 400 kilos of enriched
uranium be handed over while Iran's
ballistic missile program be subject to
severe restrictions.
Iran, however, isn't having any [music]
of it.
Iranian officials argue that nuclear
energy is a sovereign right and thus
non-negotiable.
They are willing to temporarily
>> [music]
>> limit some aspects of the program in
exchange for sanctions relief and
economic normalization.
As this graph shows,
the talking points are extremely complex
and with zero trust between the parties,
>> [music]
>> it is simply impossible to bridge the
gaps in a matter of weeks.
Addressing each and [music] every
sticking point is going to take time,
lots of time.
What Iran is lacking currently is
deterrence.
But with Trump's [music] deal and the
lifting of the sanctions,
Iran will rebuild its economy,
infrastructure, and of course
deterrence.
It will take time, yes, but what is a
decade or two in [music] the grand
scheme of things, really?
For Israel,
this is a nightmare. It's a pyrrhic
victory.
Meaning they've technically won, but at
such [music] a high cost that it is
essentially defeat in the long term.
And that's precisely [music] what
Netanyahu is trying to undo or prevent.
But while Netanyahu may have had key
influence up to this point, especially
in initiating the US-Iran war,
he has little to say as to how or when
the conflict ends. The negotiations are
primarily between Washington and Tehran.
Israel is not driving the process.
And this feed
right here confirms as much.
If the memorandum of understanding is
signed,
and it plays out exactly or as fluently
as agreed upon,
hostilities between the United States
and Iran will gradually cease.
This then creates
space for a new round of negotiations
focusing [music]
on all the other complications, such as
opening the Strait of Hormuz, the
lifting of US sanctions, et cetera.
If everything goes flawlessly, then
eventually the process will lead
to the normalization
of relations between Iran and the US.
Once that happens, once the memorandum
is signed, the blame game will begin.
Netanyahu will point the finger at Trump
and argue that the US [music] failed to
achieve political objectives, while
Trump will blame Israel for overreaching
in Lebanon.
But one thing Trump
>> [music]
>> will likely be careful with
is not to be baited by Netanyahu into
renewing hostilities with Iran, not like
last time.
>> [music]
>> So, from an Israeli perspective,
they need to really derail the upcoming
deal between the US and Iran. There's
just too much at stake.
And this is why the Israelis want to
resume hostilities.
They believe Iran is now at its weakest,
its military capacity has diminished,
and its proxy forces, such as Hezbollah,
are under pressure.
At the same time,
Israeli officials fear that the Trump
deal may leave parts of Iran's nuclear
program intact or
postpone complex decisions until later
negotiations.
And it does look like that's the case.
The nuclear sticking points are being
postponed to a later date, while the
reopening of the Strait of Hormuz, which
in itself has little consequence to
Israel, has taken top priority.
Now, for clarity,
the Israelis do not fear a bad agreement
[music] because it ends the war.
They fear a bad agreement
because it could leave Iran as a
threshold nuclear state
and allow it [music] to grow stronger
over the years and eventually
attack Israel
at a time and place of its choosing.
That is strategically dangerous for the
state of Israel, existentially even.
Let's just go to the country real quick.
You see, Israel has a terrible
geography.
At its widest point, that would be here,
it is only about 110 km across.
But, at its narrowest point, here in the
north,
the distance from the West Bank [music]
to the sea is only 17 km. And
this right here tells you everything
[music] you need to know.
It is precisely for this reason that
Israel will never relinquish [music]
control of the West Bank and allow for
the formation of an independent
Palestinian state.
Without the West Bank, Israel has
no strategic depth whatsoever.
17 km leaves no space to withdraw,
regroup, and counterattack.
Strategic depth is essential for
national security. It determines how
much time one has
to recover from an initial attack.
Space and time
are perhaps the two most important
components to warfare.
Like, even with the West Bank, Israel
only has
63 km of depth.
But, without the West Bank, its
existence
becomes close to impossible.
And this is also why the Israelis
keep expanding settlements into the West
Bank. It has no plans of relinquishing
control.
Here's what the situation looks like as
of now. Area B is where there is
civilian Palestinian control, but with
Israeli security.
There is no
territorial cohesion to speak of. The
West Bank today is
just a collection of loose clusters.
And that's precisely the point.
When there is no geographic continuity,
there cannot be an independent [music]
state.
Anyway, the point is that Israel cannot
tolerate defeat at its borders.
A setback would only give it at most 110
km in which to [music] retreat, and this
geographic vulnerability shapes just
about [music] everything in Israeli
military doctrine.
Since the day of its inception,
Israel has had to prevent attacks by
initiating combat, by preemptively
hitting its neighbors,
>> [music]
>> and defeating hostile forces early in a
war.
The only time the Israelis were caught
off guard was during the 1973 attack by
Egypt and Syrians, which had been armed
and coordinated by the Soviet Union.
Israel was on the verge of being
overrun.
And the only [music] thing that saved
the country was the fact that the
Egyptians, the Syrians, and the Soviets
had not anticipated early success, and
the forces on the ground were stunned
>> [music]
>> as what to do next, which gave the
Israelis the necessary time to regroup
and counterattack.
Israel won that war, but it did not
solve its strategic dilemma. The lack of
strategic depth is what drives Israeli
policy makers to effectively expand
Israel's borders outward.
Most notably right now is the Israeli
[music]
push into Lebanon.
The Israelis are looking to exercise
control up to the Litani River, thereby
limiting access to Israel [music] itself
by non-state actors such as Hezbollah.
However, the problem with [music] this
is that
even with the amount of territory taken
as buffer, [music]
it is still not enough to eliminate the
threat posed by Hezbollah and groups
[music] like it.
New weapons continue to develop. Think
of hypersonic missiles, fiber optic
drones, high energy lasers, AI-enabled
systems, [music] and much more. These
weapons will stress the Israeli military
to its limits.
Meanwhile, the relationship between the
United States and Israel
is one that was really formed by the
realities of the Cold War and then
renewed by 9/11.
But as time [music] passes and new
generations of lawmakers come into
office,
national interests will eventually
change along with them.
There is no guarantee that the United
States
will always be an ally of Israel.
So, for Netanyahu and his government,
the momentum
is now.
A memorandum of understanding between
the United States and Iran [music]
right at this moment in time
would cancel years of conflict and
hard-won gains
and give the initiative to Iran, which
would then,
>> [music]
>> in years from now, come back to haunt
Israel.
This is then precisely why
Israeli forces are currently bombing
Lebanon.
The intent is to provoke the Iranians
into overplaying their hands
and then forcing the political talks
with Trump to collapse.
And it almost happened on June 8th. Iran
launched several waves of missiles
toward military bases in central and
southern Israel. It was the first such
direct exchange of fire since the
ceasefire in April.
And the attack came in response
to an Israeli strike on Beirut a day
earlier during renewed fighting with
Hezbollah.
After Iran's attack, Israel then
retaliated with air strikes against
[music] military targets inside Iran,
and this brought the two very close to a
broader confrontation.
It was only after intervention by Trump
that the Israelis and Iranians agreed to
step back from further escalation. But
the exchange [music] highlights the
nuances of the ceasefire and all the
finer political interplays.
Israel is trying to preserve freedom of
action against Hezbollah even as the
United States tries to preserve the
ceasefire between Israel and Lebanon and
advance diplomatic talks with Iran.
Meanwhile,
Iran is signaling that Lebanon is part
of the broader regional ceasefire
and that any Israeli attack on Hezbollah
would trigger
an Iranian response.
For weeks now, Iran has warned
that Israeli attacks on Hezbollah,
especially in the capital Beirut, would
be seen as a violation of a larger
[music] ceasefire. Trump, however,
has been trying to separate the Lebanon
front from the diplomatic channels in
Iran. So,
by launching missiles at Israel in
response to events in Lebanon,
Iran is sending a clear message the two
fronts are connected. The Iranians are
now trying to reinforce that idea.
But this also shows us
that Iran is increasingly negotiating
from a position of relative strength.
Now, neither Iran nor the United States
want to restart hostilities.
But the recent exchange [music]
shows just how quickly Israeli action in
Lebanon can spill into a fight with Iran
and thereby threaten the negotiations
with America.
But what's more,
>> [music]
>> in October, possibly sooner, Israel will
hold elections.
>> [music]
>> So, in the next round of attacks,
Netanyahu will face pressure,
domestic pressure, to retaliate more
decisively and project strength ahead of
the election season.
Ultimately,
at a fundamental level, the strategic
objectives of the United States and
Israel differ greatly. Netanyahu wants
to weaken Iran, roll back its regional
influence, and [music]
eliminate nuclear risk.
Trump, on the other hand, wants to end
the war, [music] stabilize the region,
stabilize energy markets, reopen the
Strait of Hormuz, and secure a
diplomatic exit, even if it is less than
perfect.
If that process moves forward, the
fighting would then gradually give way
to a diplomatic [music] track. And this
is where Israel's options
become really more complicated.
Israeli policy makers would then
start to look for ways to undo the deal,
to disrupt [music] it,
but not in a way that
it openly turns against Washington.
So, pressure would become very indirect.
For example, Israel could amp up its
[music] intelligence campaign. It could
look for evidence that Iran is hiding
nuclear material or violating the terms
of the understanding. Even a small
violation could be used to argue that
the entire process is flawed.
Israel could then
>> [music]
>> increase military pressure on Iranian
proxies as a means of provoking Tehran
into overreacting.
It could also take the fight to
Washington D.C.
where Israeli groups could redouble
their lobbying efforts in Congress
or leak intelligence to pressure
American lawmakers.
>> [music]
>> And it's effort like these that could
risk collapsing the diplomatic track
altogether.
So while American policy makers see a
deal with Iran as the [music] end of a
crisis,
the Israelis see it as the beginning of
something even more dangerous. [music]
Now before we wrap up a quick note about
Delta Sweep, everything you saw in this
episode is available inside the
platform. It brings together maps,
[music] live data, maritime traffic,
military activity, infrastructure, and
open source intelligence into one
dashboard.
And frankly, that's how we've been able
to spot unusual developments before
they're reported by the mainstream
headlines. [music]
And by signing up, you can get access to
the very same dashboard. If you go to
the annual plan, the price is just $6 a
month. But that price will not stay
there forever. [music]
As we add more tools, more data layers,
and more features,
the price will go up permanently. So
this is the cheapest Delta Sweep will
ever be.
And anyone who signs up in the next 7
days
will [music] have that $6 a month locked
in
for as long as their account is [music]
active.
So even
in 5 or 10 years, your price will remain
the same.
There is a 7-day trial at sign up.
So don't overthink it.
Try it and see for yourself.
The value you get is insane. Go to
deltasweep.com
and get that early bird discount.
Anyway, that's all we have for today.
Thank you for watching
>> [music]
>> and sticking with us until the end.
Ansaru.